Hi everyone.
I'm very excited to be the one to start
this panel of my presentation
is titled Poetry of Movement, Affect and Virality in Warsan Shire’s Home.
I'm going to
look at the process of virality
when something and more specifically
a poem, goes viral in digital spaces.
How does that impact its reception,
the way that people react to it?
So the ethos of movement that lie
at the heart of internet virality,
interacting complicated ways
with the spatial and temporal esthetics
of digital platforms, producing new
literary, affective and political regimes.
When a text goes viral on the internet,
the questions that I'm asking is
what happens to the impact generated by it
as it is repeatedly encountered?
Does it lose its sense of uniqueness
and creativity upon subsequent readings?
Or alternatively, does it acquire
new layers of meaning in the process?
Given the dizzying pace
of viral phenomena, it is quite difficult
to situate them
within traditional critical frameworks.
For the purpose of this presentation,
I will use movement as an entry point
into studying viral poems
and how they produce meaning and affect
within digital spaces.
In the case of internet poetry.
The sense of spatiality
is significantly different
as the fictional
and materiality of the page and the book
is replaced by the fluidity of the screen.
While there have been multiple critics
written about this,
for the purpose of this presentation,
I'm looking at Anna Munster,
who studies the figure of the clone
as being emblematic of contemporary
digital culture, drawing attention away
from the sameness of clones.
Munster focuses instead on the genealogy
of mutations, fluctuations and failures
that constituted serial history, thereby
drawing attention to the unacknowledged
role of differential relations
in arranging, sequencing, and replicating
the codes of digital culture.
Digital space,
then, is characterized by this continuous
serial repetition, albeit
with variable differentials.
It's composed of an ensemble of different
elements, and hence the manner
in which these combinations form,
interact, and impact upon each other.
That data means the experience
of inhabiting digital spaces.
Poetry is also one of the elements
that enters into a combination
with the others, borrowing
from the model of the clone
and the series of repetitions
engendered by it.
One can argue that the experience
of reading a poem in digital space
is characterized by repetition,
but each encounter is slightly different
owing to the constantly
changing nature of constituent elements.
This lack of fixing
this means that such poetry remains
lodged in the space between the familiar
and the unfamiliar,
potentially producing
a sense of disoriented or uncanny ness.
While the act of rereading
can also be done with print based poetry,
it requires conscious volition
on the part of the reader.
In the case of digital ecology,
it is built into the very network
architecture of the space itself.
The algorithm that defines these spaces
facilitate and rewards
repetitive encounters with texts
and narratives, unintentionally,
perhaps producing an uncanny reading
atmosphere.
This slightly unsettling digital space
also translates to the poetic subject
being rendered uncanny, as a poem travels
to the labor and time pathways
generated by digital algorithms,
the poetic subject is repeatedly
reinterpreted and remediated.
In some ways, digital space accentuates
the traditional role of deformities
often ascribed to poetry itself.
It stimulates new ways of thinking
and feeling about the subject.
As readers encounter the poem through
junctions, junctures, flows, and networks.
In the next
few slides I'm going to focus on, I'm
going to study Watson
and titled Home or Conversations
About Home, which became quite popular
online in the years beginning
from 20 1516, and became a rallying cry
for the plight of refugees in the backdrop
of the Syrian refugee crisis.
But these are just excerpts from the poem
that perhaps we'll come back to later.
This is a rough timeline
of the kind of digital life and life
outside of digital spaces
that this poem has had.
So her poem titled
following titled home, a shorter,
condensed version of the original poem
called Conversations About Home,
published a few years earlier, details
the harrowing journey undertaken
by the speaker as a refugee
who is forced to leave home.
I want to start talking
about the different spaces
that featured in the poem,
starting with the one in the title
that is home.
Throughout the poem, the word home assumes
multiple configurations.
It assumes present through personification
as a predator, while simultaneously
rings risks erasure as its clearing
absence is made visible to the betas.
So in the very first stanza, home
is the mouth of a shark, a threatening,
nefarious presence which is gradually deep
ameliorated through the poem and becomes
completely unrecognizable by the end
as the refugee is forced to move
through airport toilets, boats, carriages,
refugee camps and prisons.
Home as a space loses its traditional
associations of comfort and safety
and becomes eventually the mouth
of the shark, barrel of a gun, etc.
in the last two stanzas, we'll see that
there's a quickening of pace as the home
acquires a decisive instrumentality.
For the first time, we hear the speaker
directly say that I want to go home,
but her desire is violently frustrated
by dangerous configurations
the home has acquired for her.
The home now forces its inhabitants
to leave, crawl, wade, drown.
All words with suggest movement.
Through hurried and abrupt departure.
The final act of unmoving
takes place in The Last Panther,
when the personified home
asked if inhabitants to run away from me.
Now I don't know what I have become.
I want to
move on to what I said
right in the beginning,
which is the entry point that I'm looking
into to try to understand how this poem
moves, both in terms of movements
within the poem, but also movement.
The way that the poem moves through
digital spaces
is, is to try and understand
movement itself in different ways.
So the first strand of that
is movement away
from home,
as it is documented in the poem itself.
I also want to look at how the poem
discusses the idea
of cartographic divisions, borders
within the poem and the movement
across these borders, and then go on to
the more metaphorical understanding
of the word movement in terms of how
it moves people to feel in a certain way,
or to act, or how it becomes, acquires
these kind of political underpinnings.
And then to the movement
that is engendered
by the medium of the poem
itself, by digital spaces
in and through the infrastructures
or the Ford instead of digital platforms.
The first one, we've already discussed
how the movement
away from,
but also a desire to return to home,
is documented in the poem
The Other One with the other form.
The second form of movement
that I'm talking about is the one
related to material geographies.
A critic, Jennifer Leach, has argued that,
or gestures towards the deathly danger
of the watery passage from Somalia
to yacht through the image of the shark
which opens and closes the poem.
While the names of any
geographical locations are not mentioned
specifically, the specter of the ten year
journey that the refugees undertake
haunts the poem.
Lines such as no one
puts their children in a boat
unless the water is safer than the land,
convey the horror of the situation
where refugees are forced
to undertake such journeys.
These forms of movement forge
new affective pathways through the globe,
which challenge
the rigidity of cartographic divisions.
Lisa understands this process
as Shire's attempt at enacting new spatial
and affective materiality,
and further argues that her poetry defies
any attempts to her medically seal
of certain areas and creates
connections through voicing the horrors
of civil war and human suffering,
which does not stop at geographical
or imagined borders.
The materiality of the movement
through different locations is imbued
with great affective intensity,
generating alternative encodings.
Geographical passages.
This ability
of the poem to foreground movement
and simultaneously recontextualize
it is perhaps productive
if we think of it in terms of something
that's been called poetics.
In the Literature of Migrants
by Kevin Potter.
Supporters introduced that this concept
and defines it in stark opposition
to send in what he calls
the sedentary metaphysics,
which invite the tendency to think
of mobile people in ways that assume
the moral and logical primacy of fixity
in space and place, on the other
hand, understands migrant literature
as providing an index of movement.
The territorial creative
becoming, and force.
How does this sense, a kind of poetics,
relate to the forms of spatiality
represented by the poem?
In other words,
how does the poetics of movement
reconfigure the topography
characteristics of the poem?
While there are multiple places
featured in the poem,
none of them are specified in geography
or national terms.
In that respect,
one can classify the poem as graphical
or a local descriptive poem.
Nevertheless, the poem still comments
on the ramifications
of geographical spatiality and limitations
it imposes on immigrants
in the form of cartographic boundaries.
Now we move on to the other.
The third kind of movement
that I'm looking at,
which is this kind of movement
through media, through digital media.
More specifically,
this quality of movement intrinsic
to the poem is further complemented
by the poem's accelerated motion
through digital spaces,
as the poem travels through the assemblage
of multiple, varying elements
that constitute the spatiality
of digital platforms, every encounter
with the poem materializes new forms
of engagement and reading practices,
which in turn produce intimacy
between the poem and the reader.
In this way, motion is becomes a function,
or movement becomes a function,
both of the formal attributes of the poem
and the space where it is
circulated and read.
It must also be noted here
that travel and movement is deeply rooted
in Shire's process of writing itself
that can be traced to certain
Somalian traditions of oral and archiving,
called the tradition.
In the Somali poetry,
the bar is the type of specifically female
words, traditionally
a palm traditionally associated
with feminine spaces and activities.
In an interview, Shire states that poetry
so integral
to Somali culture
that it's not high culture.
This commonplace ordinariness of poetry
lends it a peculiarly personal
and intimate tonality,
as it becomes a form of expression
and communication that is integrated
into the very structure of the community.
When this locally specific poetics,
steeped in the oral traditions
of Somalia, travels in
and through digital spaces, it is itself
transformed and simultaneously
transforms the reception of such poetry.
And finally, then, to
the last kind of movement
that we are speaking of,
which is the more like I said, movement
in the more metaphorical sense
of the word.
It moves how it moves, it really does.
As his poems move through digital spaces
and come into contact
with virtual bodies,
they are moved from one state to another.
The repeated encounters
with the same text, or in certain cases,
slightly modified versions, leads
to an intensification of affective value.
The idea of affect as contagion,
of course,
is something that's
well documented in affect theory.
So I'm thinking about Sarah Emma's
idea of stickiness to refer to the uncanny
affective quality which moves people and
urges them into varying form of actions.
Similarly, Susanna Personen has developed
the concept of resonance to address
the oscillating registers of affect
that alter in their qualities,
rhythms, speed, and intensities.
For both of these critics,
the affective is intricately entwined
with the material, as resonant encounters
have the power to move the user's body
from one state to another.
In other words,
the activity has political consequence
as it turns to the material world
and becomes an alternative modality
of political participation,
so the feeling itself becomes a warmer
political source.
Finally, I just want to in conclusion,
I just want to sort of draw attention
back to the to the two meanings
of the word movement that I've used here,
which is the literal and metaphorical.
So movement, as you see it,
within the poem, movement as it happens,
as the poem moves
unsupervised through digital spaces
and then movement as,
as an aspect of association of the poem
and how all of these three come together
in very complicated ways to perhaps
produce new forms
of reading, new forms of being affected,
and new forms of reception.
That's what. I'll leave you with that.
Thank you so much.
And just
right.
Thank you.